Guide to the Marion Meade Papers on Dorothy Parker
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Marion Meade Papers on Dorothy Parker
1859-2008.
Meade, Marion, 1934-
9 linear ft.,(18 document boxes; 1 Flat Box #317).
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027
4079662
This collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, notes, notebooks, illustrations, photographs, audio cassettes, and printed materials related to Meade's research on Dorothy Parker.
Biographical Note
Author and biographer of Dorothy Parker.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, notes, notebooks, illustrations, photographs, audio cassettes, and printed materials. The correspondence consists of letters from colleagues and acquaintances of Dorothy Parker, American author, essayist, and poet, and letters with Meade's publisher. Among the cataloged correspondents are Saul Bellow, Malcolm Cowley, E.B. White, and Richard Wilbur. The manuscripts consist of two drafts of Meade's book, accompanied by hard bound and paperback versions of the book. The subject files are arranged in two series: chronological, following her draft outline for the book; and topical, in alphabetical order. These research files contain photocopies of correspondence and writings of Dorothy Parker, a Parker bibliography, and related literary and biographical clippings and articles. The notebooks consist of a research draft event outline for the book. The illustrations are primarily mock-ups for the book and drawings not used in the book. Photographs consist of both those used in the book and those not included. The 56 audio cassettes are of Meade's interviews with people who knew Dorothy Parker, along with selective transcripts and a related log.
1992 Addition: A file of photographs and brochures relating to the 1992 commemorative stamp issued by the U.S. Postal Service has been added.
1994 Addition: Printed materials about the Parker Centenary have been added.
Arrangement
Arranged in eight series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Arranged Correspondence
Series III: Manuscripts
Series IV: Subject Files, Chronological
Series V: Subject Files, Alphabetical
Series VI: Audio Cassettes
Series VII: Oversize Folders 1-2 Subject Files: Alphabetical
Additional 1
Subjects
United States Postal Service.; Parker, Dorothy, 1893-1967--Biography.; Bellow, Saul.; Cowley, Malcolm, 1898-1989.; Fiedler, Leslie A.; Gellhorn, Martha, 1908-1998.; Hahn, Emily, 1900-; Hayes, Helen, 1900-1993.; Matthau, Walter.; Morris, Wright, 1910-1998.; Mumford, Lewis, 1895-1990.; Robson, Flora, 1902-1984.; Sayre, Nora.; Schulberg, Budd.; Smith, Scottie Fitzgerald.; Vanderbilt, Gloria, 1924-; White, E. B. (Elwyn Brooks), 1899-1985.; Wilbur, Richard, 1921-; Authors, American--20th century.; Announcements.; Audio cassettes; Bibliographies.; Biographies.; Correspondence; Drawings.; First drafts.; Fliers.; Genealogies.; Illustrations.; Manuscripts for publication.; Menus.; Negatives.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Outlines.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Photoprints; Postage stamps.; Programs.; Releases.; Slides.; Transcripts.; Biographers; Dramatists.; Satirists.; Theater critics.; Women authors, American.; Women dramatists.; Women poets.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 2-18. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
12/18/1989 M-89-12-18 Marion Meade Gift
10/12/1992 M-92-10-12 Commemorative stamp file U.S. Postal Service Gift
02/21/1994 M-94-02-21 Parker Centenary Meade, Marion Gift
Gift of Marion Meade, 1989 & 1994. Gift of the U.S. Postal Service, 1992.
- Series I; Cataloged Correspondence
  - Addams, Charles (Box 1)
  - Barry, Ellen (Box 1)
  - Bellow, Saul (Box 1)
  - Booth, Shirley (Box 1)
  - Cowley, Malcolm (Box 1)
  - Fiedler, Leslie (Box 1)
  - Gelhorn, Martha (Box 1)
  - Hahn, Emily (Box 1)
  - Hayes, Helen (Box 1)
  - Matthau, Walter (Box 1)
  - Morris, Wright (Box 1)
  - Mumford, Lewis (Box 1)
  - Robson, Flora (Box 1)
  - Sayre, Nora (Box 1)
  - Schulberg, Budd (Box 1)
  - Smith, Scottie (Box 1)
  - Vanderbilt, Gloria (Box 1)
  - White, E.B. (Box 1)
  - Wilbur, Richard (Box 1)
- Series II: Arranged Correspondence
  - A to L (Box 1)
  - M to Z (Box 2)
- Series III: Manuscripts
  - Dorothy Parker: "What Fresh Hell is This?" t.m.s. (1st draft) with soft cover edition (Box 3)
  - Dorothy Parker: "What Fresh Hell is This?" (setting copy) with hard cover edition (Box 4)
- Series IV: Subject Files, Chronological
  - Introductory material and research material, 1893-1919 (Box 5)
  - 1920-1926 (Box 6)
  - 1926-1933 (Box 7)
  - 1930-1939 (Box 8)
  - 1940-1954 (Box 9)
  - 1955-1967 (Box 10)
- Series V; Subject Files, Alphabetical
  - Bibliography - Corrections (Box 11)
  - FBI - Genealogy (Box 12)
  - Goodner - Notebooks (Box 13)
  - Parker - Photos used (Box 14)
  - Vanessa - Works (1940-1967) (Box 15)
- Series VI: Audio Cassettes
  - Audio cassettes (1) of interviews (Box 16)
  - Audio Cassettes (2) of interviews (with related logs and transcripts). (Box 17)
  - Marcovicci, Andrea. "What is Love" [incl "I Wished On The Moon" & "The Red Dress" by Parker] (Box 17)
- Series VII: Oversize Folders 1-2 Subject Files: Alphabetical
  - 1. Illustrations not used in book (Box Flat Box 317)
  - 2. Illustrations used in book (mock-ups) (Box Flat Box 317)
- Series VIII: Addition
  - Marion Meade. Dorothy Parker: What Fresh Hell Is This (New York: Penguin, 2007) (Box 18)
  - Marion Meade "Ladies of the Corridor" t.m.s. (author's copy with corrections) (Box 18)
  - Dorothy Parker and Arnaud D'Usseau. The Ladies of the Corridor (New York: Penguin, 2008) (Box 18)
  - Arnaud D'Usseau. 2 audio tapes and 1 cd on Parker (Box 18)
  - American Theatre (April, 2008) (Box 18)